<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grounds of infant-baptism briefly explained</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2138C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222580</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833734</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42248)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2209:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grounds of infant-baptism briefly explained</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Lawrence, at the Angel in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38212:1"/>
            <head>THE GROUNDS OF Infant-Baptiſm Briefly EXPLAINED.</head>
            <p>GOD's Word plainly declareth, That it is ſufficient Qualification for Baptiſm, if Perſons be Believers<hi>: If thou believest withal thine heart, thou mayest be baptized,</hi> Act. 8. 36, 37. <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the goſpel to every creature. He that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mark 16.15, 16. Now the Infants of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents are either Believers, or Unbelievers; or neither Believers nor Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, but a third kind, middle between both. A third kind of Perſons, who are neither Believers nor Unbelievers, but middle between both, cannot be, the Scripture knoweth none ſuch, it is contrary to the Tenour of God's Word, and to the Grounds of Religion, and to the Common Belief of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and will <note place="margin">Ubi ponis parvu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los baptizatos? Profecto in nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero credentium Auguſt. de Verbis Apoſtoli Ser. 14.</note> infer one of theſe two impious Abſurdities; either that Infants are bruit Beaſts, or that dying in Infancy, they are neither ſaved not damned, but remain in a Third State, middle, between Heaven and Hell, for ever. If you ſuppoſe the Infants of Chriſtian Parents to be Unbelievers, then in reaſon you muſt ſuppoſe, that they be all ſo, and dying in Infancy Unbelievers, they muſt needs be damned. For Chriſt plainly ſaith, That <hi>he which believeth not, ſhall be damned, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already, he ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> Mark 16. 16. John 3. 18, 36. And if all the Infants of Chriſtian Parents, dying in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, are damned Unbelievers, we have much more reaſon to conclude, that all the Infants of Heathen Parents dying in Infancy are ſo too. But, ſure, that Doctrine cannot be true, which adjudgeth all Infants taken away in Infancy to inevitable Damnation for ever. It remains then, that the Infants of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are Believers, and therefore baptizable.</p>
            <p>§ II. Though Infants are not capable of actual Faith, after the ſimilitude of vigilant grown Men, yet they are capable of the inward Seed and Root thereof, after the ſimilitude of grown Men in their Sleep, while their Sleep <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 9. Luk. 1. 15, 35. Jer. 1. 5.</note> laſteth, and as <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>John Baptist</hi> were ſanctified from the Womb, and as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38212:2"/>
the Infant Jeſus was holy, and as <hi>David</hi> was <hi>made to hope when he was upon his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 9.</note> 
               <hi>mothers breasts.</hi> The Soul of each Infant is a Spiritual Subſtance, and being ſo, it muſt needs be immortal, and ſome way or other in act, from the time that it is put into the Body, and while it is in the Body, it doth animate and quicken the Body, and is the Life thereof, and is always upon its way to Eternity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 14.</note> all ſtop or ſtay, and either it is by ſupernatural Grace inwardly <hi>holy</hi> in the ſight of God, and ſo in the way to Heaven: or it is deſtitute of ſupernatural Grace, and then it is inwardly unholy and <hi>unclean</hi> in the ſight of God, and ſo in the way to Hell. Our Brethren, the Oppoſers of Infant Baptiſm confeſs, That from <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> the Common Parents of us all, <hi>corrupted Nature was conveyed to all their Poſterity, deſcending from them by ordinary Generation, being now concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Sin, and by Nature Children of Wrath, the Servants of Sin, the Subjects of Death, and all other Miſeries, Spiritual, Temporal, and Eternal, unleſs the Lord Jeſus ſet them free.</hi> Now Infants being inwardly infected and defiled with Sin and Corruption, as the Great Diſeaſe of lapſed Humane Nature, they muſt needs be by Divine Grace capable of Cure and Remedy, which Cure and Remedy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without ſuper natural Regeneration, whereby their Souls are inwardly renewed and made Partakers of the Divine and Godly Nature, conformably to the Image of the Infant Jeſus, whoſe Soul, while he was an Infant, did overflow <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4. H b. 1. 9. &amp; 2. 11, 12. Rom. 8. 29. Joh. 20. 17. Luk. 1. 35. &amp; 2.40. Joh. 3. 3, 5, 6.</note> with the Seed of Divine Faith, Hope, Love, Meekneſs, Piety, and all other Coeleſtial Graces, a degree and meaſure whereof God worketh in all Elect Infants, in reſpect whereof the Infant Jeſus, and they are Brethren and Fellows, there is ſpiritual ſimilitude between them. The Infant Jeſus is conſiderable two ways: Firſt, In reſpect of the Natural Subſtance of his Soul and Body; and ſo there is ſimilitude between him and all other Infants: for they alſo have Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, no leſs than the Infant Jeſus: this ſimilitude is natural and common. Secondly, In the Infant Jeſus, beſides the natural Subſtance of his Soul and Body, there is by ſupernatural Grace, and gracious Donation and Endowment, the Seed and Root of all Divine and Heavenly Vertues, which are the Life of the Soul, like as the Soul is the Life of the Body; theſe Divine and Heavenly Vertues did emidently ſhine forth in the Life of Chriſt, when grown up. <hi>Jeſus increaſed in wiſdom and ſtature, and in favour with God and man.</hi> The Seed and <note place="margin">Luke 2. 52.</note> Root of all Heavenly Vertues was by ſupernatural Grace in his Soul, while he was in the Virgin's Womb, and as ſoon as he was born of her, but did not appear till he was arrived to ſome maturity. When he was grown to Man's Eſtate, he did uſe to take his Reſt in Sleep; and while be ſlept, the inward Heavenly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Graces of his Mind did not appear, but the Seed and Root thereof lay hid in his Soul. Now between ſuch Infants as <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>John Baptist,</hi> who are by ſupernatural Grace born of God, and holy from the Womb, and the Infant Jeſus, there is ſpiritual and ſpecial ſimilitude. But between Infants unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and unholy, and the Infant Jeſus, there is no ſpiritual and ſpecial ſimilitude; <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15. Iſa. 42. 1. Rom. 9 8.</note> but contrariety, as between the Seed of the Serpent, and the Seed of the Woman, between Non-Elect and Elect. No reaſon can be rendred, why the Infants of Chriſtian Parents, ſhould not be as truly capable of being Believers, as the Infant Jeſus was of being a Saviour. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you is born this day, in the city of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2. 11. Mat. 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>David, a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord. She ſhall bring forth a Son, and thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus: for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins.</hi> As if you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Infant Jeſus Chriſt not to be the Saviour of Souls, it cannot be declared, when he comes to be the Saviour of Souls. So if you ſuppoſe the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents not to be a kind of Believers, it cannot be declared when the Children born of Believing Parents, come to be in the Number of Believers, in what Year of their Lives. If the Infancy of Jeſus Chriſt could not barr him from being Jeſus Chriſt, the Mediator between God and Men, the Head of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38212:2"/>
Church, and the Saviour thereof, when he ſucked his Mother's Breaſts. By the ſame reaſon the ſtate of Infancy cannot hinder the Children of Believing Parents from being a kind of Bellevers and Members of the Church, when they ſuck their Mother's Breaſts. Chriſt plainly ſays, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall offend one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.6. Luke 18. 15. Mark 9. 36.</note> 
               <hi>of theſe little ones which believe in me,</hi> &amp;c. And by comparing the Evangeliſts it will appear, that by <hi>theſe lettle ones which believe in Christ,</hi> he means Infants, ſuch as <hi>Christ took in his arms;</hi> at leaſt, he doth not exclude Infants.</p>
            <p>§ III. The Adverſaries of Infant-Baptiſm expreſs their Doctrine in theſe words<hi>: Thoſe who do actually profeſs Repentance towards God, Faith in, and Obedience to,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 97.</note> 
               <hi>our Lord Jeſus, are the only proper Subjects of Baptiſm:</hi> And for proof hereof, they refer us to two Scriptures in the Margin, namely, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 36, 37. Now from theſe very Scriptures it is already proved, That it is enough for Baptiſm that Perſons be Believers, and that the Infants of Believing Parents are a kind of Believers, and therefore proper Subjects of Baptiſm. But no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture declares, that thoſe only who actually profeſs Belief, are the proper Subjects of Baptiſm, this is plainly an addition to God's Word, and therefore to be rejected.</p>
            <p>§ IV. Chriſt's Commiſſion to his Apoſtles is, <hi>Go ye, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghost:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19.</note> That is, Go ye, and Chriſtianize all Nations, make all Nations Chriſtians, Saints, Believers, Diſciples of Chriſt, get them into Covenant with God, through Chriſt, and then Baptize them, and ſolemnly enter them into the Church of Chriſt, by the Rite of Baptiſm: For like as <hi>Jeſus made and baptized Diſciples;</hi> firſt made, and then baptized Diſciples; ſo we may reaſonably think, that <note place="margin">Joh. 4. 1, 2.</note> Chriſt's Commiſſion to his Apoſtles was, That they ſhould firſt make all Nations Chriſtians, Saints, Believers, Diſciples, and get them into Covenant with God through Chriſt, and then baptize them. At the time when Chriſt gave forth this Commiſſion, the whole World was either Jews or Gentiles. The generality of the Gentiles were, for the preſent, Worſhippers of Idols, under the Power <note place="margin">Acts 26. 17, 18. Eph. 2. 12.</note> of Satan, drowned in Ignorance, Infidelity, and falſe Religion. The Jews had been long uſed to Circumciſion, the Paſſeover, and the reſt of the Old Teſtament-Miniſtry and Pedagogy: too many of them were Unregenerate, though Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the true God: the reſt, who were truly Godly, did yet need Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerning the true Meſſias, and that this ſame Jeſus whom we Preach, is the Chriſt of God, the Saviour of the World, the ſole Mediator between God and Men, foretold by the Prophets, and prefigured in ancient Types and Sacrifices, and that all the Old Teſtament-way of Worſhip was now to ceaſe, and give place to the New. Therefore the ſcope and true meaning of Chriſt's Commiſſion may well be thought to be this: <q>Go ye, my Apoſtles and Miniſters, into all the World, and Preach the Goſpel to every Perſon capable thereof; reduce them from their Ungodlineſs and State of Damnation, to a State of Grace and Salvation; make them Chriſtians, Saints, Diſciples, Believers, Members of the Church; get all, both Parents and Children, into Covenant with the true God, through Jeſus Chriſt; throw down the Middle Wall of Partition between Jew and Gentile, and make both One Holy Society in Chriſt: and having ſo done, Baptize them, and let Baptiſm be the Token, Sign, and Seal of the Covenant, between God in Chriſt and them.</q> If then the Infants of Chriſtian Parents be a kind of Chriſtians, Saints, Believers, Diſciples, Members of the Church, in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, through Chriſt, (all which for ſubſtance denote the ſame thing, and are convertible) then by the Tenour of Chriſt's Commiſſion they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38212:3"/>
are to be Baptized. Now the Oppoſers of Infant-Baptiſm own and declare, that <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 115, 116.</note> the Infants of Believing Parents under the Old Teſtament, were in Covenant with God: and therefore they muſt needs own and agree, That the Infants of Believing Parents under the New Teſtament, are no leſs in Covenant with God; unleſs they can prove that God's way is not equal; which they never can: For certainly his way is equal, as himſelf declares; but the ways of Sinners are <note place="margin">Ez. k. 18. 25.</note> unequal.</p>
            <p>§ V. It is plain from <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 10, 11, 12, 13. that Little Ones, together with their Parents, did enter into Covenant with the God of Iſrael: And from the time of <hi>Abraham</hi> God ordained, that all his Male-Seed, ſucceſſively in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, ſhould be Circumciſed the Eighth Day; by that Rite a Divine Bond and Engagement was laid upon the Infants Circumciſed, to be the Lord's faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <note place="margin">Acts 7. 8. Gen. 17.9, 10, 11.</note> Servants all their days, it was <hi>a token of the Covenant between God and them.</hi> And long before Circumciſion, even from the Beginning, there were by Divine Appointment Sacrifices, which were typical and ſymbolical of Eternal Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, through Faith in the Death of Chriſt, as future. In thoſe Sacrifices Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents did Covenant with God: <hi>Gather my ſaints together unto me: thoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 5.</note> 
               <hi>that have made a covenant with me by ſacrifice.</hi> They did alſo inter their Infants into Covenant with God, they did firſt devote and conſecrate themſelves to the Service of the true God, and engage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Themſelves to him, and then their Infants; the reſolution of every pious Parent being the ſame with <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s: <hi>As for me and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſ. 24. 15.</note> 
               <hi>my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> The mutual Oath and Covenant between the Nation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> did bind their whole Off-ſpring and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; <note place="margin">Joſ. 9. 2 Sam. 21.</note> which becauſe King <hi>Saul,</hi> ſome Hundreds of Years after, did preſume to violate, therefore God did ſeverely revenge the Breach thereof, by Three Years Famine, in the Reign of King <hi>David,</hi> and would not be pacified but by the Death of Seven of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Sons, the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſo deſiring. From all which it is plain, that Parents may by Authority from God, lay a Divine Bond, Oath, and Covenant, upon the Souls of their Infants, which when grown up, they are bound inviolably to obſerve.</p>
            <p>§ VI. There was a Covenant between God and Chriſt conſidered as Man, That he ſhould be obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs, and be therefore Rewarded and Crowned with ſupereminent Joy and Glory in Heaven for ever: The Foundation and Corner-ſtone of this Covenant was laid in Chriſt's Incarnation, according to the Eternal Purpoſe and Fore-knowledge of God, the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. And hereupon the Infant Jeſus was Circumciſed the Eighth Day, in Token of the foreſaid Covenant between God and that bleſſed Babe: And about the Thirtieth Year of his Age he was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> which was another Token and Confirmation of the ſame Covenant. And, look, as <hi>Moſes</hi> bore up his Heart in all his Sufferings, by having <hi>reſpect unto the recompence of the reward:</hi> ſo the Man Chriſt Jeſus <hi>for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 11. 26. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 12. 2. Iſa. 49 4 &amp; 53.11. Phil. 2. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the throne of God;</hi> according to the Covenant between God and him. Now the Covenant between God and the Man Chriſt Jeſus, is for ſubſtance the ſame with the Covenant between God and all godly Chriſtians, they are ſpecifically but one everlaſting Covenant, becauſe Chriſt conſidered as Man, <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 9. &amp; 2. 11, 12. Rom. 8. 29. Joh. 20. 17. Col. 1. 18.</note> and all godly Chriſtians are Brethren and Fellows, only he in all things hath the pre-eminence, as being the Firſt-born among many Brethren, and anointed with the Oyl of Gladneſs above his Fellows.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38212:3"/>
§ VII. <hi>What advaniage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Much every way.</hi> Certainly the Chriſtian now hath not leſs advantage then the Jew anciently had, and there is not leſs profit now by Baptiſm, then was of old by Circumciſion. Chriſtian Parents and their Seed, are not Loſers, but rather Gainers by the Coming of Chriſt, and the New Teſtament in his Blood: becauſe he is <hi>a ſurety of a better teſtament, the mediator of a better covenant.</hi> But this cannot be, if the Infants of Chriſtian Parents be not admittable to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm. <note place="margin">Heb. 7.22. &amp; 8 6.</note> For how can that be a better Covenant and Teſtament, which aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Circumciſion, whereby there was much Profit and Advantage to the Infants of Believing Parents anciently, and gives them nothing in lieu thereof, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them from Baptiſm coming in the room thereof?</p>
            <p>§ VIII. That Baptiſm comes in the place of Circumciſion is evident: <hi>for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law.</hi> For thô the Law for Circumciſion was in force ſome Hundreds of Years before the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Levitical Prieſthood, yet were they both but temporary Inſtitutions, deſigned to laſt but for a time, <hi>until the time of Reformation;</hi> which being come, <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 10.</note> they ceaſe and have an end, and in their room comes Baptiſm, and the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, and the New Covenant in his Blood: Plain it is, that as there is a change of the Levitical Prieſthood, ſo is there alſo of Circumciſion: <hi>If ye be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>circumciſed, Christ ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> Now there cannot be a change of Circumciſion, but there muſt needs be another Sign and Token of God's gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Covenant in its room: for therein conſiſteth the nature of a change, and the change here muſt needs be for the better, becauſe Chriſt is the Mediator of a better Covenant; and the time of the New Teſtament is the time of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, more glorious than the time of the Old Teſtament. Accordingly Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is better then Circumciſion, as better ſuiting with the State of the Church under the New Teſtament: 1. It is more eaſie, Circumciſion was bloody and painful. 2. It is more plain and ſignificative of our Communion and Fellowſhip with Chriſt in his Death and Reſurrection, and of the waſhing away of all our ſins in his Blood. 3. It is equally applicable to Males and Females. 4. It is not limited to the Eighth Day. 5. It is enjoyned to all Believers, both Jews and Gentiles, throughout the World. 6. It is to continue to the End of the World. 7. It is to be done by none but a Valid Miniſter of Chriſt. 8. It is to be done publickly in the Aſſembly of God's People, if it may be. Look then, as we have the Lord's Supper in the room of the Paſſeover, and the Lord's Day in the room of the Seventh Day Sabbath, and the Prieſthood of Chriſt in the room of the Levitical Prieſthood, and the New Teſtament in Chriſt's Blood in the room of the Old Teſtament in the Blood of Beaſts: So we have Baptiſm in the room of Circumciſion a change every way for the better. Either Circumciſion is changed for Baptiſm, or for nothing: for no other thing imaginable comes in its room. But a change there muſt needs be, otherwiſe the Scripture will be found erroneous in ſaying: <hi>The Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ IX. The Oppoſers of Infant-Baptiſm deny Baptiſm to be the Seal of God's Covenant with every Believer, and affirm, That <hi>the Scriptures are altogether ſilent thereof,</hi> and <hi>conceive the Seal of that Covenant, is the Indwelling of the Spirit of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 117,</note> 
               <hi>Christ, in the particular and individual Perſons in whom he reſides, and nothing elſe.</hi> But this is a manifeſt Error<hi>:</hi> for before Abraham was Circumciſed, he was a true Believer, in Covenant with God, and ſealed with the Spirit of Chriſt:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38212:4"/>
afterward <hi>he received the ſign of circumciſion, a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of the faith, which he had yet being uncircumciſed.</hi> So that beſides the Indwelling of the <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 11.</note> Spirit, there was then clearly another Seal of God's Covenant, namely, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion. The difference between theſe two Seals ſtood in this: the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of the Spirit is an internal Seal, peculiar to the Elect, of abſolute <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 13, 14. &amp; 4, 30. 2 Cor. 1. 22.</note> neceſſity to the Salvation of each Perſon from the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> to the end of the World; but Circumciſion was an external Seal, common to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> to Elect and Non-Elect Perſons, not ordained before <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time, neither to all then, but to ſome only, and to no Infant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Eighth Day, and upon ſpecial Reaſons diſpenſed with or omitted for Forty Years in the Wilderneſs, and never eſteemed by God of equal excellency and neceſſity with Regeneration. Moreover, it is undeniably plain, that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was <hi>a token of the covenant between God and Abraham, together with his ſeed after him, in their generations.</hi> And being ſo, it was a Seal thereof: <note place="margin">Gen. 17, 9, 10, 11.</note> for a Token of God's Covenant, and a Seal thereof, for ſubſtance, denote the ſame thing. This Covenant did aſſure the earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Natural Seed in common by <hi>Sarah,</hi> and the heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his Spiritual Seed. Thoſe of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed who reſted in the Letter of Circumciſion without the Spirit, in the Circumciſion of the Fleſh without the Circumciſion of the Heart, and minded the earthly more than the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s degenerate Seed, Children of the Devil, born after the Fleſh and not after the Spirit, ungodly, and liable to eternal Damnation. But ſuch as together with the Circumciſion of the Fleſh, had the inward Circumciſion of the Heart, and by ſupernatural Grace and Regeneration were truly holy before God, theſe were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual Seed, Elect in Chriſt, Children of God, and Chriſtians really, though not ſo called, and unto them Circumciſion was principally a Seal and Token of God's everlaſting gracious Covenant, and of pardon of Sin, Juſtification, Adoption, and Eternal Life, as an abſolute and free Gift in Chriſt<hi>:</hi> And though only the Male-Infants were Circumciſed, yet as to all Fundamental Bleſſings of the Covenant, the caſe of Males and Females was the ſame. And though Circumciſion be long ſince aboliſhed, yet the Doctrine thereof is not aboliſhed, it is truly Evangelical, and of perpetual uſe to the Church Militant unto the end of the <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 21.</note> World. Again, it is plain that Baptiſm is a Figure: <hi>The like figure whereunto, even baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us.</hi> This is equivalent to a Sign, Seal, and Token of Salvation, according to the New Covenant in Chriſt's Blood: For it is certain, that the Salvation of Souls is not ſave by the New Covenant in Chriſt's Blood. Now ſeeing that Baptiſm is a Divine Figure, ſuch as doth ſave the Soul, it muſt needs be a Sign, Seal, and Token of God's everlaſting Covenant in Chriſt with every Believer, whereby is Salvation. And Chriſt's Commiſſion to his Apoſtles, as is before ſhewed, being to get all Perſons into Covenant with God through Chriſt, and then to baptize them, and it being manifeſt that the Infants of Chriſtian Parents are in Covenant with God through Chriſt, it followeth unavoidably that they are to be Baptized, and admitted to Baptiſm as the Seal and Token of God's Covenant coming in the room of Circumciſion.</p>
            <p>§ X. The Adverſaries of Infant-Baptiſm, from Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> alledge, That <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 118, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> the forecited Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. is not exactly tranſlated, and conceive the Sence of it to be this: <q>And he received the Sign of Circumciſion, a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, which was to be in the Uncircumciſion. Which was to be, (I ſay) not which had been, not that which <hi>Abraham</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38212:4"/>
had whilſt he was yet Uncircumciſed, but that which his Uncircumciſed Seed ſhould have; that is, the Gentiles, who in time to come ſhould imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Faith of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </q> This they <hi>earneſtly deſire may be ſeriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ighed.</hi> Now ſuppoſing, but not granting this Sence of the words, it overthrows their forenamed Poſition, that nothing but the Indwelling of the Spirit is the Seal of God's Covenant with every Believer: for here they plainly grant another Seal, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumciſion a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith in us Gentiles, and conſequently of God's Covenant with us. But the truth is, that the foreſaid Sence of the words from Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts itſelf and the Grounds of Religion: For it ſuppoſes Believing Gentiles to be Imitators of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and yet ſaving Faith in us Gentiles to differ in kind from the Faith of <hi>Abraham:</hi> which is very Abſurd and Atheological. For how can we imitate the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> if his Faith and ours be two contrary kinds? There may be degrees of ſaving Faith, but two kinds of ſaving Faith there cannot be, from the Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> to the End of the World. <hi>Abraham</hi> was ſaved by the Grace of Chriſt, as purpoſed to be Mediator through Faith: and the Saints now are ſaved by the Grace of Chriſt, as already Mediator through the ſame kind of Faith. So that if Circumciſion was a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith in time to be in us Gentiles, of neceſſity it could not but be a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of the Faith which <hi>Abraham</hi> had before he was Circumciſed; becauſe his Faith then, and our Faith now, as to Eternal Salvation, are for ſubſtance one and the ſame kind. Hence he is <hi>ſtiled the Father of all them that believe, though</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 11.</note> 
               <hi>they be not circumciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ XI. The Wiſdom of God ſpeaking by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> thought this abundantly ſufficient to ſilence and ſtop the Mouths of all Gain-ſayers: <hi>Can any man forbid water that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 10. 47.</note> 
               <hi>holy Ghost as well as we?</hi> Now though receiving the Holy Ghoſt may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude both principal and ſubſervient Gifts and Bleſſings, yet it cannot be thought to exclude thoſe which are principal and ſupream, but rather they above all other are included as moſt excellent and neceſſary, <hi>viz.</hi> Pardon of Sin, Juſtification, Adoption, Regeneration, a State of Salvation. The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Interrogation doth plainly declare this to be the Mind and Will of Chriſt, and the true meaning of that Grand Commiſſion, <hi>Go and teach all Nations, baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. that none be excluded from Baptiſm, that have received the Holy Ghoſt ſo as to be in a State of Salvation: And therefore if according to the Rules of wiſe and conſcientious Charity, in the due mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween too much Rigour and too much Laxneſs, we have juſt grounds to judge, that the Infants of Chriſtian Parents be in a State of Salvation, we may apply the foreſaid Interrogation concerning them: <q>Can any Man forbid Water that theſe Infants of Chriſtian Parents ſhould not be Baptized, who in the judgment of Charity are beloved of God, Pardoned, Adopted, Regenerate, Partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, ſo as to be in a State of Salvation as well as their Parents and grown Bellevers?</q>
            </p>
            <p>§ XII. It cannot be thought that we ſhould be bound infallibly to know the Hearts of others: for if we muſt not baptize but upon thoſe grounds, we muſt baptize none at all; not grown Perſons themſelves. Of neceſſity there muſt be a Standard of Admiſſion to Baptiſm, and it muſt be plain, univerſal, ſerving for all Perſons, in all Places, at all Times, immovably fixed by God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38212:5"/>
otherwiſe there will be endleſs Diſpute, Uncertainty, and Contention about it. Infallible inſight into, and knowledge of others Hearts and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences inwardly, belongs only to God, and is to us impoſſible, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unneceſſary. Therefore Chriſtian Charity in the Breaſts of God's Miniſters, avoiding the two extreams of Rigour and Licentiouſneſs, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt to judge, diſcern, decide, and determine who are, and who are not to be reputed Saints, Chriſtians in Covenant with God through Chriſt, in a State of Salvation, and conſequently fit for Baptiſm, and to be waſhed in the Laver of Regeneration: <hi>For can any man forbid water, that all ſuch ſhould not be baptized?</hi> This Standard is plainly Divine; if you go from it, you know not where to fix.</p>
            <p>§ XIII. That well known place in the Goſpel, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is abundantly enough for the Regulation of our charitable Judgment, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Charity in this point being ſo full, clear, and pregnant: For Chriſt readily received ſuch Infants as were brought unto him for his Bleſſing, was much diſpleaſed with thoſe that would have hindered them from being brought unto him, he took them up in his Arms, that his Hands upon them, and bleſſed them, and commanded, ſaying, <hi>Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Now though Chriſt be not corporally preſent on Earth, as ſometime he was, for to have Infants brought unto him for his Bleſſing, Grace, and Favour, yet he is ſpiritually preſent in the Aſſemblies of his Saints, and with his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the right Diſpenſation of Baptiſm, according to his Word alway, <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 1. Mat. 18. 20. &amp; 28. 19, 20.</note> even unto the end of the World. But Chriſtian Charity binds us to judge all the Infants of Chriſtian Parents, whilſt they are Infants, to be in a State of Salvation, till being grown up they manifeſt the contrary. Who can doubt but that the Infants of godly Parents are as dear to God, as beloved by Chriſt, as holy, as fit for Heaven, as much in a State of Salvation, as <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> as multitudes more ſuch grown Perſons baptized by the Apoſtles, and as many baptized by the Oppoſers of Infant Baptiſm? <q>Can any Man forbid Water that the Infants of pious Parents ſhould not be baptized, which belong to the Kingdom of God, as well as their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents?</q>
            </p>
            <p>§ XIV. There is difference between the Doctrine of Baptiſm, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 1, 2. 1 Cor. 1. 17. 1 Pet. 3.21.</note> itſelf, as between Morals and Rituals, between Subſtance and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, between Mercy and Sacrifice, between Principal and Appendix: <hi>For Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the goſpel.</hi> The Doctrine of Baptiſm is the Doctrine of the New Covenant, of which Baptiſm is a Divine Sign, Seal, and Token<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Sum of it is this, That all Men are reducible to Two, the Firſt and the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> and all ſuch as deſcend from the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by Natural Generation: are conceived and born in Sin, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15 45.47. Joh. 3 3 5. Gal. 3. 21. Act. 4. 12. Rom. 8. 29. 1 Pet. 1. 2.</note> from the Guilt whereof they cannot be ſaved and ſet free, without ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Regeneration through the Grace of Chriſt, the Second <hi>Adam</hi> and all ſuch as God from everlaſting did fore-know, would by his ſpecial Grace in Chriſt be Regenerate, and have Spiritual Life in their Souls, them he did predeſtinate to eternal Salvation. This Doctrine of Baptiſm is the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true Religion, the Marrow of the Scripture, the Sum of Practical Truth, and the Compendium of Divinity. But Baptiſm as diſtinct from the Doctrine thereof, is but a Divine Figure, Ceremony, or Token annexed to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38212:5"/>
the Goſpel or New Covenant, a Ritual Ordinance, the Contempt whereof is perllous, but Infants are not capable of contemning it.</p>
            <p>§ XV. There are Three ſorts of Bleſſings and Favours vouchſafed by God to Fallen Man; ſome common to Chriſtians and Heathens; ſome not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to us and Heathens, and yet common to good and bad Chriſtians; ſome peculiar to God's Elect. Of the Firſt ſort are Rain and fruitful Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, having our Hearts filled with Food and Gladneſs, Magiſtracy, Civil Order, and the neceſſary Supports of Humane Society, whereby the worſt on Earth are in better caſe than the Devils and damned Ones in Hell, and are capable of being ſaved by God's Grace, in ſuch ſort as our firſt Parents, and the Angels which fell, were capable of Perſeverance. Of the Second ſort are the Word and Sacraments, being born of Chriſtian Parents, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Chriſtian Religion, and Communion in external Ordinances, and Priviledges common to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> to Elect and Non-Elect Chriſtians, ſuitably to their Age and Capacities. Of the Third ſort are Regeneration, Adoption, Pardon of Sin, Juſtification, Perſeverance, Eternal Life; theſe are peculiar to God's Elect, and not common to them and others. And then doth God Elect Perſons in Chriſt, when according to his own Eternal Purpoſe and Fore-knowledge, he doth for the ſake of Chriſt, and his meritorious Croſs and Interceſſion, without all precedent Merit of their own, by his Goſpel-work in them, Divine Faith, and thereby pardons their Sins, and ſeals them with his Holy Spirit, and ſo ſets them apart for himſelf, and of Dead in Sin, the Slaves of Satan, and Reprobate to every Good Work, makes them alive unto Righteouſneſs, the Children of God, his Elect Ones, a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People to himſelf. Thus the Death of Chriſt is the meritorious cauſe of our Election to Salvation, but not of God's Eternal Purpoſe to Elect us; for Divine Purpoſe to Elect, and Election itſelf, are clearly diſtinct as Cauſe and Effect, as Antecedent and Conſequent, and may in no wiſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</p>
            <p>§ XVI. I conceive, that all the Three forementioned ſorts of Bleſſings and Favours are proper Fruits and Effects of Chriſt's meritorious Croſs and Paſſion, though they are not all equally ſo, but moſt eminently and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally the Third ſort, peculiar to the Elect, and the other as ſubſervient: For Chriſt <hi>is the Saviour of all men, eſpecially of thoſe that believe:</hi> and whom he ſaves, he ſaves by the merit of his Croſs. God doth not now Govern the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 10. 2 Pet. 2. 1. Heb. 2.9.</note> World barely as Creator, before <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, but as Redeemer in and through Chriſt, unto whom all Power is given in Heaven and Earth, and his Kingdom ruleth over all, both Angels and Men, for the everlaſting Good of all Militant Saints, and in order to carrying on the Great Work of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by Faith, in all ſuch as belong to the Election of Grace. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever Bleſſings and Mercies, whether common or ſpecial, any of fallen Mankind partake of ſubſequently to Creation and Permiſſion of Original Sin, they are proper Fruits and Effects of Chriſt's Death. And wherein <note place="margin">Col. 1. 20. Eph. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 21.22, 23. Phil. 2. 8 9 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 28. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 23 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 9. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Rev. 5. 9 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 13.</note> any Intellectual Creatures, whether Angels or Men, are capable of being ſerviceable to God, and to Chriſt our Mediator, in promoting the Work of Redemption, they are bound to ſerve to the utmoſt of their power, and Chriſt may be ſaid to have purchaſed their Service with his Blood, and to have right thereto by the Merit of his Croſs<hi>:</hi> For in purchaſing <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38212:6"/>
               <hi>Redemption,</hi> which is the principal end, he muſt needs be ſuppoſed inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively to purchaſe all the neceſſary helps and means requiſite and conducing thereto, <hi>Et qui adimit medium dirimit finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ XVII. Concerning Heathen Parents the Scripture plainly declares, That for the preſent they are <hi>without Christ, being aliens from the Commonwealth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the Covenants of Promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the world.</hi> We cannot think that the Infants of ſuch are in Covenant with God. As of old it was rightly ſaid, <hi>Salvation is of the Jews:</hi> ſo now it is rightly ſaid, That Salvation is of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. <note place="margin">Joh. 4. 22.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> But we cannot ſay, that the Infants of Heathen Parents are added to the Church. <note place="margin">Act. 2. 47.</note> While the Jews continued in the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> their Infants were <hi>the natural branches, and partaked of the root and fatniſs of the Olive-tree;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 15. Rom. 9.4. &amp; 11. <hi>from</hi> 16. <hi>to</hi> 25. Act. 2. 39. Iſa. 44. 3.</note> to them and their Children pertained <hi>the adoption, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi> But they by Unbelief breaking themſelves and their Children off from the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his true Religion, this gave occaſion for the calling of the Gentiles, who were <hi>wild by Nature, and Branches of the wild Olive-tree:</hi> but being by ſupernatural Grace and Regeneration united to Chriſt, endued with the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo <hi>graffed contrary to Nature into a good Olive-tree:</hi> Now the Infants of Believing Gentiles are become the Natural Branches, and together with the Infants of believing Jews, <hi>partake of the root and fatneſs of the olive-tree,</hi> and conſequently of Baptiſm, as coming in the room of Circumciſion. By this good Olive-tree, I underſtand Chriſt, the Saviour of all Men, ſpecially of thoſe that believe, who hath with his own Blood purchaſed Temporal Mercies for all Men in general, and Eternal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for the Elect in ſpecial, and Baptiſm in common for all Chriſtian Parents and their Infants.</p>
            <p>§ XVIII. As <hi>they are not all Iſrael, which are of Iſrael:</hi> ſo they are not all <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 6.</note> the Church, which are of the Church, nor all internally in Covenant with God, that are externally in Covenant with him. And yet all that are of the Church, and externally in Covenant with God may be admitted to ſuch external Priviledges, as do in common pertain to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> to <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> to viſible Chriſtians and their Seed, ſuitably to their Age and Capacity.</p>
            <p>§ XIX. Baptiſm in its own nature is <hi>the Laver of Regeneration,</hi> a ſaving <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 21. 1 Pet. 3. 21. Rom. 4. 11. Act. 22. 16.</note> Figure, a divine Sign, Seal and Token of Pardon of Sin, Adoption, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Eternal Life, according to God's gracious Covenant in Chriſt. But as one and the ſame Sun doth harden Clay and ſoften Wax, and as one and the ſame Goſpel is to ſome, through God's ſpecial Grace in Chriſt, the Savour of Life unto Life, and unto others, through their own Sin, the Savour of Death unto Death, ſo is Baptiſm. In receiving Baptiſm, Perſons receive <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16, 17. 2 Cor. 6, 1.</note> the Grace of God; but too many <hi>receive the grace of God in vaih:</hi> and ſo what in its own nature is the Laver of Regeneration, a ſaving Figure, a divine Sign, Token, and Seal of the greateſt Bleſſings and Favours, is not ſo to ſuch as receive it unworthily and in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38212:6"/>
§ XX. The Papiſts generally, and many Proteſtants, hold, That the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments confer Grace, <hi>Non ponentibus obicem,</hi> to ſuch as do not put in a barr. <note place="margin">Roffenſ. Cont. Luther, Art. 1. Le Blane Theſ. Theol. de uſu &amp; efficacia Sacram. Novi Teſtam.</note> 
               <hi>Luther,</hi> in the beginning of the Reformation, did cenſure and oppoſe this Sentence and Opinion as Heretical. Certain it is, that there cannot be a Sacrament without Faith: For all ſound Divines unanimouſly approve that excellent Saying of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s, <hi>Accedit verbum ad Elementum, &amp; fit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum:</hi> The Word comes to the Element, and it is made a Sacrament. This Saying is grounded upon theſe and the like Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. So that without the Word of Divine Inſtitution, there is no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no Baptiſm, no Lord's Supper. But the Word of Inſtitution cannot be without Faith, either common or ſpecial: For the Word of Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Faith are related as principal and Inſtrumental, and as related they are by Nature together, and do mutually prove and infer each other. There may be Words and Waſhing without Faith, but not Chriſtian Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm. Common Faith, ſuch as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had, is ſufficient to the Validity of Baptiſm, and for entring the Perſon baptized into the Lord's Oath and Covenant, and into the Number and Society of viſible Chriſtians, as to external Fellowſhip and Communion; but it is not ſufficient to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of Sin, and a State of Salvation; for this there is an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſpecial Faith, even the Faith of God's Elect as to the Adult, and the Divine Seed thereof as to Infants. No Chriſtian Faith, no Church, no Sacrament, no Goſpel-Miniſtry, no Difference between us and Heathens, nothing but Practical Atheiſm, and the Kingdom of the Devil, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deſpair.</p>
            <p>§ XXI. Many hold that God's Promiſes are of two ſorts, Abſolute and Conditional, and that Baptiſm is but a Seal of his Conditional Promiſes, and that the eternal Salvation of Infants is not abſolutely and entirely by the Grace of God in Chriſt, but partly by it, and partly by ſomewhat elſe as a condition thereof, or cauſe, <hi>Sine quâ non,</hi> without which Infants cannot be ſaved. But the Scripture hath no ſuch Doctrine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may not be received. 1. We read, That <hi>all the Promiſes of God in Christ, are Yea, and in him, Amen.</hi> And that <hi>godlineſs is profitable unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 20.</note> 
               <hi>all things, having promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> But of two ſorts of Divine Promiſes, ſome abſolute, and ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, <note place="margin">1 Tim, 4.8.</note> we read nothing at all. 2. The Sum of all the Bleſſings and Good Things contained in God's Promiſes, is Eternal Life, as begun on Earth and perfected in Heaven: <hi>In hope of eternal life, which God that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lie; promiſed before the world began,</hi> Tit. 1. 2. <hi>And this is the promiſe that he hath promiſed us, even eternal life,</hi> 1 John 2. 25. Now Eternal Life is God's own Life, even <hi>the Life of God.</hi> But the Life of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18.</note> be conditional for if it be conditional, then God himſelf muſt needs be conditional, uncertain of his own Life, an impotent, and precarious God, dependent upon Men for his very Life, and it is at their courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie whether he ſhall be God or no. 3. If the Eternal Salvation of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, from firſt to laſt, be not abſolutely and entirely by God's Grace in Chriſt, then we muſt be bound to pray for Infants after this manner<hi>:</hi> Lord, do not ſave them, but almoſt ſave them; the matter is divided into certain parts, part belongs to thee, and part belongs to ſome other; Lord, do thine own part, it pertains not to thee to do more, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38212:7"/>
we may beg no more, thou art but a half Saviour, an imperfect Saviour, there be others co-equal and co-ordinate with thee in this matter. But this kind of praying is rather blaſpheming than praying. 4. If Infants eternal Salvation, from firſt to laſt, be not abſolutely and entirely by God's free Grace in Chriſt, then it muſt needs be wholly of Debt, and not of Grace, and ſo Infants ſhall have ground of glorying againſt God after this manner, and to this effect: We thank God indeed for making us Infants, and for bare univerſal Grace in common with <hi>Cain, Judas,</hi> and the reſt of damned Men in Hell, when they were upon Earth; but for our Eternal Salvation as begun on Earth, and perfected in Heaven, we owe God no thanks at all; but he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to us by our Parents, or by our Nominal God-Parents, or by our ſelves, for our good Merits and Deſervings, and not we at all to him, for any ſpecial and differencing Grace. Which Doctrine is the ſame with <hi>Pelagianiſin,</hi> plainly repugnant to Faith in God: For God is not God, unleſs he be abſolutely <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 35. 36. 1 Cor. 4. 7.</note> and entirely the Author of all Good to his Creatures, whether it be natural or ſupernatural corporal or ſpiritual, common or ſpecial, temporal or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, it is all from God of Grace, and not of Debt, whether they be Infants or Adult Ones who partake of it. 5. Though God make uſe of Inſtruments and Means, and there can be no pardon of Sin without foregoing Divine Faith in the Adult, and the Seed thereof in Infants, yet Means ard Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 6. &amp; 15. 28. Pſal. 145. 17 18. Iſa. 40. 17, 18. Eph. 1. 11.</note> and ſubordinate Cauſes and Agents, add no Perfection to God, he is truly <hi>all in all,</hi> and <hi>worketh all in all;</hi> but ſo that he is no way the Author of Sin, but the juſt Avenger of it; the Author of all Good, holy in all his Ways and righteous in all his Works, working all things after the Counſel of his own Will, and the whole Creation abſtracted from, compared with, and ſet againſt God, is as nothing; yea, leſs then nothing, and vanity. 6. In ſuch ſort as God in Scripture is ſaid to repent, by way of Anthropopathy and condeſcenſion to our weakneſs: ſo he may be ſaid to have conditional Promiſes, and to promiſe Eternal Life, upon condition of Faith and Repentance; but no otherwiſe: For like as the Scripture aſſures us, and all agree, that God is not a Man that he ſhould repent: ſo by the ſame reaſon God is not a Man that he ſhould be bound, and Debter, and promiſe Eternal Life conditionally. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 11 29. Numb. 23. 19. Gen. 6. 6. <hi>Hilar. de Trinit. lib.</hi> 10.</note> For it is a Maxime in Divinity, taken from St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> and grounded upon the deepeſt Reaſons and Foundations of ſupernatural Religion, that, <hi>In abſoluto nobis &amp; facili est aeternitas:</hi> Eternal Life cannot conſiſt in uncertainty, waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuſpenſe, and dubitation; which neceſſarily it muſt, and cannot be avoided, if it be but conditional. For what is Eternal Life, but God himſelf as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in Eternal Bleſſedneſs? Conſequently to ſay, that Eternal Life is not abſolutely certain, but conditional, is in effect to ſay, that God is but condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally God, uncertain of his own Life, and ſo is not true and very God, but an Idol, a Figment of Man's Invention.</p>
            <p>§ XXII. Excepting the Infant Jeſus, who was abſolutely holy and ſinleſs, every other Infant doth ſuffer what it ſuffers for its own ſin, its own inward pravity and corruption, is the ſole meritorious <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all the <note place="margin">Nullus unquam ita ſomniando deliravit, ut magnum iſtum defectum, quo Natura humana primi hominis praevaricatione vitiata eſt, ex aliquo Dei pacto cum parentibus initio, vel ex poſitiva Dei lege aut voluntate propagari arbitretur. Janſen, de Statu Naturae lapſae, l. 1. c. 17.</note> puniſhment laid upon it by God, and the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> is but the <hi>occaſion.</hi> Original Sin in Infants, is the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> but not the <hi>Effect</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38212:7"/>
His eating of the forbidden Fruit was his own Perſonal Sin, and yet the Sin of all Mankind; becauſe he in that inſtant was all Mankind, there being no other Man then in being. But God gave him Repentance and Pardon of that and all his other Sins, and therefore his eating of the forbidden Fruit is not impured to us, no Man's Conſcience doth ſmite him for it; but all the Sin imputed by God to Infants, is only that inward Corruption that is latent in their Souls, which the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> hath occaſioned, but not cauſed<hi>:</hi> For though he was truly penitent and pardoned, and ſo alſo was our firſt Mother <hi>Eve,</hi> in the inſtant of their Natural Coition, and Conjugal Act, yet there did then cleave to their Souls inordinate Luſt and Concupiſcence, and this <hi>Ex Naturâ rei,</hi> from the nature of the thing, did by God's moſt righteous Judgment and Permiſſion, unſearchably <hi>occaſion,</hi> but not <hi>cauſe</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin, and ſinful Contagion, in all their Natural Off-ſpring. <hi>This Diſtinction of the Cauſe and Occaſion, if well heeded, both fully acquitteth God's Juſtice, and abundantly reconcileth the ſeeming Contradictions of Scripture in this Argument</hi> of puniſhing Children for Parents Sin, ſaith B. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> in his Third Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Ad Populum,</hi> p. 180. Edit. 6. Firſt God made <hi>Adam</hi> holy, next he permitted his Sin, then he gave him Repentance and Pardon, through Faith in Chriſt, the promiſed Seed: afterward he made him a Common Head and Root to all his Natural Off-ſpring by Natural Generation, according to his own Eternal Purpoſe, to his own Children immediately, to the reſt of the World remotely, as I humbly conceive.</p>
            <p>§ XXIII. Chriſtian Parents are the fitteſt to preſent their own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Baptiſm, and to undertake for their good Education; they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are their proper God Parents, becauſe they are ſo by Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Nature makes them Parents, and Chriſtian Faith makes them Godly Parents, and ſo they are by Divine Ordination God's Agents, Servants, Sureties, and Truſtees, to ſee to the Baptiſm and good bringing up of their Children, and are accountable to him. Whereas thoſe who are commonly called God-Parents, properly are not ſo, they are but nominally ſo; becauſe they are, what they are not by Divine, but by Humane unneceſſary Inſtitution. And therefore, where by the 29th Canon of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> touching Baptiſm, it is ordained, That <hi>no Parent ſhall be urged to be preſent, nor be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to anſwer as Godfather for his own Child:</hi> It ſhould rather be ordained, That except in caſe of Sickneſs, or other the like impediment, each Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parent ſhall be urged to be preſent at the Baptiſm of his own Child, and undertake for its good Education, and, under Chriſt, be reputed the moſt proper Godfather; and the forenamed Canon ſhould be aboliſhed, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſtian Meekneſs and Equity, and ſavouring of Unchriſtian Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour.</p>
            <p>§ XXIV. Though Chriſtian Parents are the next Inſtruments of preſenting their Children to Baptiſm, and procuring this favour for them; yet it is the <note place="margin">Offeruntur par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuli ad percipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem gratiam, non tam ab eis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum geſtantur manibus, quamvis &amp; ab ipſis, ſi &amp; ipſi boni &amp; fideles ſunt, quam ab univerſa Societate Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum atque fidelium. Ab omnibus namque offeri recte intelliguntur, quibus placet quod offeruntur, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Sancta atque individua Charitate ad Communicationem Sancti Spiritus adjuvantur. Tota ergo hoc mater, quae in Sanctis eſt, facit<hi>:</hi> quia tota omnes tota ſingulos parit. Auguſt. Epiſtol. 22.</note> whole Society of Godly Chriſtians upon Earth, who under God, and the Lord Jeſus, are the moſt Noble and Eminent Inſtruments of all Spiritual
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38212:8"/>
Good to the Souls of Infants, not excluding, but rather including their Parents, if they be truly godly, them eſpecially; for thus we read: <hi>But Jeruſalem which is above is free, which is the mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4. 26. This <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Holy Catholick Church, the bleſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of all faithful People, is the Mother of us all, and conſequently of all ſuch Infants as belong to the Election of Grace. And we have great reaſon to think, that all ſuch Infants as God's Word binds us to baptize, dying in Infancy with the Seal and Token of God's gracious Covenant upon them, are elect and ſaved, eſpecially if they be the Infants of godly Parents, they are, <hi>Cives Eccleſiae,</hi> Citizens of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhe is ſpiritual Mother to them all, and every one: <hi>For by one Spirit are we all bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 13.</p>
            <p>§ XXV. We may admit the Infant to Baptiſm, and yet not admit his Parents to the Lord's Supper; becauſe it may be wholſome Penalty to deny them the Lord's Supper, till they have reformed their profane and wicked Lives; and yet it may be too much Rigoun to debar their Infant from Baptiſm. Not ſeldom the Children of wicked Chriſtian Parents, when grown up, prove godly, and are ſaved: and too many Children of godly Parents, when grown up, prove wicked, and periſh. As God may by his common Grace move the Heart of a carnal Chriſtian Parent to pray, to joyn in Prayer, to hear the Word, to give an Alms, to devote part of his Eſtate to pious and charitable Uſes, and by God's common Grace, he may be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for Temporal and Eternal Good to others, though himſelf prove a Caſt-away. So by the ſame common Grace he may be inſtrumental in God's hands, for bringing his Child to Baptiſm, and procuring it ſolemnly entred into his Holy Covenant, and may devote it to his Service, and be uſeful to its Temporal and Eternal Good, though himſelf be ungodly and periſh. Under the Law, the Infants of good and bad Parents were promiſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly admitted to Circumciſion by Divine Warrant; and good and bad <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did in common contribute towards the Building of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle firſt, and afterward of the Temple. Whom we can, we are to amend by the Word and holy Diſcipline; and whom we cannot, we are to mourn for and tolerate. Where the Tares cannot be pluckt up without endangering the Wheat, they are to be let alone, and both are to grow together till the Harveſt. There are two kinds of ſincerity, common and ſpecial: with the former, the generality of ungodly Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Parents, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of <hi>England</hi> deſire Baptiſm for their Children, they deſire it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, ſeriouſly, and without diſſembling: this is not no ſincerity, it is better then none, and yet it is not divine, heavenly, and ſpiritual. But Children born in manifeſt Whoredom and Adultery, ſhould not be baptized, unleſs the Father or the Mother, one, or both, will, at the Baptiſm of the Child, penitentlally confeſs the Sin. And the Eccleſiaſtical Judge ſhould not for filthy Lucre exempt infamous and notoriouſly ſcandalous Sinners from ſuch wholſome Penance; ſo to do is very ſinful and ſcandalous, and God's Bleſſing cannot be thought to go along with that Gain which is taken <note place="margin">Joſ. 7. 19. Prov. 28. 13. 1 Tim. 5. 20.</note> to free Sinners from giving Glory to God, by wholſome Confeſſion of Sin.</p>
            <p>§ XXVI. By Infant-Baptiſm a Divine Bond and Engagement is laid upon the Parents to teach, and upon the Children to learn, as ſoon as they ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38212:8"/>
be capable God's true Religion: This Divine Bond and Engagement doth very much tend to Godlineſs, and ſhunning Sin, by aweing the Conſciences of Parents, and Children, when grown. But the denial of Infant-Baptiſm by erroneous freeing Parents and Children from this Divine Bond and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, doth too much tend too Looſeneſs and carnal Liberty, and profane Converſation.</p>
            <p>§ XXVII. Infant-Baptiſm is greatly uſeful to keep up the Doctrine of Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin in Infants, and the neceſſity of ſupernatural Regeneration, and Eternal Redemption by the Grace of Chriſt, and ſo it is greatly uſeful to our Faith. But the way of thoſe who are againſt Infant-Baptiſm, doth very much tend to weaken our Faith herein, and make all Men think that there is no ſuch thing as Original Sin in Infants, that they have no need of Regeneration and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption by Chriſt, and that they are no leſs holy and pure then the Infant Jeſus, who was after an extraordinary and miraculous manner concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of a Virgin, and born of her: which is a great and dangerous Error.</p>
            <p>§ XXVIII. Moreover, their way tendeth to harden the Jews in their Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity: becauſe the Goſpel obligeth them to believe, that if they will become Chriſtians not only themſelves, but their Infants alſo ſhall become great Gainers, and be under a better Covenant then that of Circumciſion; which upon the Principles of thoſe who oppoſe Infant-Baptiſm, cannot be, and ſo the Jews are ſcandalized, and a Stumbling-block is caſt in their way to hinder their Converſion.</p>
            <p>§ XXIX. The Apoſtles did rightly in baptizing thoſe with the Baptiſm of <note place="margin">Auguſt. Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. cap. 49. Bedae reſponſ ad qu. 5. in fine lib. Retract. in Act. Apoſtol.</note> Chriſt, who had been before baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>John. Act.</hi> 19. becauſe <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm gave no Remiſſion of Sins, ſave through Faith in the Death of Chriſt as future, and ſo it pertained to the Old Teſtament Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which ſtood in force till after the Death of Chriſt the Teſtator and Surety of the New Teſtament<hi>:</hi> by whoſe Death, and the Inſtitution of the New Teſtament in his Blood, the whole Old Teſtament Diſpenſation, and <hi>John</hi>'s preparatory Baptiſm, as included in, or joyned with the ſame, is to ceaſe and have an end; and now Chriſt as Mediator of the New Covenant, ordains a new way for all Nations, that they be made Diſciples, and baptized in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; this is clearly a new way and kind of Baptiſm differing from <hi>John</hi>'s. But this will no way warrant the Doctrine and Practice of thoſe among us, who re-baptize grown Chriſtians, who had been lawfully baptized in their Infancy with Chriſt's Baptiſm, how they will avoid the Charge of Anabaptiſm, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful re-baptizing, I ſee not. And it may ſeem ſtrange, that they can find Evidence in the New Teſtament for the Divine Appointment of the Lord's Day, and that from the Reſurrection of Chriſt the laſt Day of the Week was changed into the firſt Day of the Week; as in their Confeſſion of Faith themſelves declare, <hi>p.</hi> 77. and yet cannot find like Evidence for the change of Circumciſion for Baptiſm, and the Baptiſm of Infants as the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38212:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
§ XXX. They tell us, That <hi>all inſtituted Worſhip receives its Sanction from <note place="margin">Their Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 115, <hi>p.</hi> 116.</note> the Precept, and is to be thereby governed in all the neceſſary Circumſtances thereof.—And that it depends purely upon the Will of the Law-giver to determine what ſhall be the Sign of his Covenant, unto whom, at what ſeaſon, and upon what terms, it ſhall be affixed.</hi> Now though much more might be ſaid in this Argument, yet neceſſitated brevity will not permit more, and I think I have ſaid enough to prove, that it is the Will of Chriſt that we baptize the Infants of Chriſtian Parents, that in ſo doing we proceed according to his Precept and Commiſſion to his Apoſtles, to teach and baptize all Nations. So hath been the Practice of the Univerſal Church to our times, God's Bleſſing hath gone along with it, and Chriſt according to his gracious Promiſe, will not fall to be with his Miniſters in the diſpenſing of it unto the end of the World, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 20.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
